Hello, I'm your host, David Bernard. My
guests today are Lucy Levy, chief
consumer officer, and Nicole Paige,
senior product manager at Zumba, the
largest branded fitness company in the
world. On the podcast, I talked with
Lucy and Nicole about how
customer-driven iteration led Zumba from
VHS tapes in 2001 to launching an app in
2024.
their app to web experiments that
boosted LTV by 17%.
And how they are able to charge for
content when countless Zumba classes are
available for free on YouTube. Hey Lucy,
thanks so much for joining me on the
podcast today.
>> Thank you for inviting us.
>> And Nicole, nice to have you as well.
Always fun to have two folks uh from the
same company to kind of have different
perspectives.
>> Thank you, David. I'm looking forward to
the conversation.
So, I wanted to kick things off with the
story of Zumba. And we don't always dive
into the story of apps, but Zumba's
really interesting. You know, it's been
around for 24 years and has kind of
become synonymous with dance-based
fitness. It's kind of the Kleenex of
fitness in that a lot of people just say
Zumba to refer to any kind of
dance-based fitness. And and that's a
remarkable achievement as a company. And
you know, the the app, as we'll get to,
is is very new to the story of the Zumba
brand. Uh, but let's go all the way back
and talk through the founding of the
Zumba app. And I think it'll be
especially interesting to folks like a
indie developer looking for that next
new app to build or a, you know,
somebody at a bigger app company
thinking about secondary product market
fit or even, you know, somebody a big
app company building a side project. Uh,
I think there's a lot of nuggets in the
story of Zumba of how to think about,
you know, what kind of product to build,
whether or not you're feeling that kind
of pull of product market fit and things
like that. So, Lucy, take it away. Tell
us the story of how Zumba was founded 24
years ago.
>> Yes. Yes. Uh, I'm happy to share the
story and being a big fan of the
podcast. So, thank you so much again for
inviting us. Funny that you say that
Zumba Clinics that that example is on
point. It happens very often that people
just think that we are fitness
discipline or a fitness category, not
necessarily a private brand. But I'll
tell you a little bit about the story.
So Zumba has been around for 24 years,
which in the fitness world is unheard of
and a lot of people had little faith
that we're going to survive that many
years, but there is a lot to it and a
lot of power into the community. So
Zumba started and it's a funny funny
story. It's three Albertos, so same
name, different backgrounds, but the
three of them are Colombians. So big
coincidence on that front. And it
actually started with Alberto Perman,
who is our current CEO and one of the
co-founders. Uh who had lost his job. He
had started a business, internet
business 24, 25 years ago that obviously
burst with the internet uh when the
internet bubble burst. And he was out of
a job, out of path. He didn't know what
to do. He was having dinner at his mom's
house and the mom said, "Why don't you
come downstairs to meet my fitness
instructor? He teaches an amazing class
that everyone wants to attend." Of
course, he was like, "Why the hell am I
going to have to meet your fitness
instructor? Like, this makes no sense."
But as every mom, uh, she was very
persistent and he finally came and they
went to meet Beetto, which is the other
Alberto. He was a successful fitness
instructor in Colombia and was just
getting started in Miami. But successful
meaning that he had a class that had a
lot of people, but he hadn't created a
brand or or or a business around it,
right? So, he was teaching at the at the
building and the class was packed. A lot
of people were outside waiting to join
the class. But the biggest insight is
that everyone was laughing and enjoying.
So, Alberto Perman, who is super
creative and very smart, he saw that
situation. He said, "You know what?
there is something here. People are
actually exercising without suffering
which is not something that we see very
commonly right especially 24 years ago.
So then you know they invited the other
Alberto who is our COO um the three of
them are still super active and involved
in the company and they decided to
create a VHS which eventually went into
a DVD to start selling online. They got
inspired by Tao and Billy Blanks. So
they started selling the DVDs through
through TV, through a license and and a
few other partners and they were getting
some success with that. But the pivotal
moment was when viewers or people that
had purchased the product started
calling the call center of the
infomercial company saying that they
wanted to become instructors or they
actually wanted to join an inerson
class. So as you know the infomercial
products normally go through a cycle
where they even if they succeed at some
point they die down and they disappear.
So they were already starting to feel
that that could happen and they were
already trying to think, okay, what else
can we do? So they decided, let's do a
training in Miami to license
instructors. Let's see how many people
show up. If more than 60 people show up,
we keep going with that idea. If not, we
all have to start thinking about what is
going to be our, you know, career path.
Uh because these DVDs were not
necessarily very sustainable long term.
So it ended up happening that about 120
people showed up to the training in
Miami. super passionate, you know, very
excited. And so they continued to
replicate that situation. So they were
training people all around the country
and long story short, a lot of those
people wanted to take the training
multiple times because they needed
support and they decided to create the
Zumba instructor network, which is our
uh core business and our biggest asset.
It is our community, our mission as a
company is to make our Zen members
successful. So how it works is that
normally you take an intro training
which is the basic one Zumba training
and then as you take that training you
have the option to join the Zumba
instructor network where we provide a
lot of benefits including apps for them
to teach uh music choreography marketing
materials license to teach around the
world. So a lot of them end up joining.
And lastly, what happened? So this
company was built based on, you know, a
customer feedback or user feedback if
you want to call it that way, just to
find parados with the app. The last
thing what happened is that people were
actually tattooing the logo of the
company and they were actually creating
clothing. So they were using white
t-shirt or whatever and they were
putting the brand in their clothing. So
the third revenue line is an apparel
brand that's pretty successful. It's
like the uniform of our instructors and
uh we sell through e-commerce and to
distributors internationally. So long
story short, the instructor license
certification is one uh part of the
business. Then the Zumba instructor
network is the second part and then
apparel is the third part. Company has
been around for 24 years. We're in 180
countries. We're super global. We have
trainings happening and instructors
teaching in 180 countries on an ongoing
basis. and we have 15 million students
taking Zumba classes on a weekly basis.
So super proud of the accomplishments.
There's one interesting data point.
There are more than 200,000 locations uh
having Zumba. There is less gyms around
the world that exist. So there are more
classes happening because they happen in
schools, in churches, in parks. So Zumba
is actually bigger than the than
actually the gym locations. But you're
all wondering how do we end up doing an
app? Obviously pandemic came a lot of
disruption specifically uh obviously in
the fitness industry and we were first
of all our initial reaction is how can
we support our instructors we stay true
to our mission so we decided that let's
not do an app to compete with our
instructors because it's not what we do
and let's actually create a system for
our instructors to to teach virtually
while while the pandemic was happening.
So, we did that. But in the meantime, of
course, we've realized that people went
back, you know, five years later, people
went back to their in-person classes. A
lot of gyms where some instructors were
teaching had shut down. So, we were
hearing from people that they wanted to
take Zumba again, but they didn't have a
class near them. Um, so that's when we
decided to do the app. We launched the
app about a year and a half ago. It's
been fascinating, a lot of learnings. We
have a class locator in the app. So the
app is mostly especially the
subscription part to access high quality
content but we all we actually have a
class locator where we can match you
with a local instructor. So eventually
once you feel comfortable you can try an
inerson class. It's been quite a ride.
We're still around. We're strong. Uh
people do Zoom around the world every
single week. So happy to be part of the
company. Such a cool story 24 years
later to now be like one of the hottest
fastest growing fitness apps on the app
store uh 24 years later and again you
know launching an app in 2024 as a
fitness brand feels late you should have
had an app in 2010 or 2012 you know
you've been around that whole time uh
but I think it is really fascinating how
um missiondriven you are and how the
instructors and the classes are so core
to the brand. Uh so Nicole, I want to
ask you, you know, as Zumba started
thinking through what could an app look
like? How do we do that and not kind of
kill what's been so successful for us?
How do we not alienate our instructor?
What was the thinking behind all of
that? How the product came to be after
the pandemic and as you started thinking
that you really did need to build an
app?
>> Yeah, definitely. So we actually at
Zumba we have a lot of experience with
apps because we have a number of apps
that we've built for our instructors. So
we have a lot of apps that our
instructors use to put together their
playlist to teach their classes to
organize their social media. But during
the pandemic when we realized that we
needed a way to bring Zumba to people
around the world who weren't able to
participate in the classes during the
pandemic we started doing a lot of
research and we went through many
iterations for the app and we tested a
lot of hypotheses during this research
but the one that we found was that a lot
of people wanted to do Zumba but they
were a little shy or they had been out
of fitness for a while and they didn't
feel comfortable going to the classes.
So the niche that we found ourselves in
that would also help our instructors was
get beginners, get people who are coming
back to fitness, get them into the Zumba
app, get them comfortable with doing
classes, and then eventually they would
go and they would find an inerson class.
So that was really our sweet spot. And
we continued to interview, we talked to
a lot of instructors, we talked to a lot
of potential students. And everyone was
telling us that they want to get
comfortable with the classes first. they
want to feel like they're confident um
so they can eventually go and find a
class.
>> I'd love to dig a little deeper there. I
think myself and so many app developers,
especially, you know, indies don't
necessarily think they have the
resources or whatever, are so bad at
user research and talking to people.
What did that look like for Zumba? Did
did you already have a lot of email? Did
you do phone calls? Did you do Zoom? Was
it a survey? How how did you actually do
that research and kind of start to
uncover the insights that then became
the app?
>> We're so fortunate as Zumba because we
have so many people that love Zumba like
Lucy mentioned, you know, tattoo getting
level of love for Zumba. So, we've
always had tons and tons of our
instructors who have been willing to
talk to us and we talked to them
regularly. when it came time to just
finding students, we did go to classes
in person and we talked to students in
classes, but we also just have a lot of
people in our database that are were
really willing to talk to us. So, we
talked to hundreds of students and
instructors over the course of the app
development, also way more than that in
surveys. So, luckily, people are really
willing to talk to us. They want us to
make Zumba better for them. So, it was
always really easy for us to find people
to talk to and we got them on Zoom, we
got them on the phone. We did a lot of
different kinds of interviews where we
would do structured interviews, but we
also did things like a study where we
tried to get them to do more workouts
throughout the week and we kind of just
treated it like a check-in and we would
let them talk to us and not ask them as
many questions. So, we did a lot of
different iterations and got a lot of
great feedback that helped us shape the
app.
>> Very cool. As you were doing that
research, how did you think about,
especially as you kind of honed in on,
you know, beginners and people returning
to fitness being where you needed to
focus? How how did you think about not
overindexing on the dieards, not
overindexing on the instructors who've
been with you 15 years, not overindexing
on the participants who have Zumba
tattooed on their arm? Uh, how did you
balance, you know, kind of filtering the
feedback of, okay, here's here's a
segment of like die hard and then, you
know, but we really do need to still
find those kind of new users to really
get that fresh perspective in addition
to the dieards.
>> Yeah, that was so important. We spend a
lot of time looking at our data and
pulling out specifically people that
downloaded the app and then churned or
took one class and then churned. And we
spend a lot of time talking to those
people as well because obviously we want
to build the app for the people that
love Zumba, but we also want to make
sure that we're bringing people in and
letting them engage with the product
enough to find the love for it. So,
we're trying to get people that churn
out early and talk to them and figure
out what is it that made you leave? What
is it that did you find another product
that works for you or did you just give
up fitness altogether? We're trying to
we spend a lot of time talking to them
as well. I would want to add um yeah
definitely cohort research. So for sure
we we're very mindful of that. But
what's interesting is that in the
findings a lot of the people that end up
turnurning is because they rather go to
an in-person class which is also a good
situation for us. So it's interesting
the findings that that we're getting.
Obviously not great for the app but
great for the business overall and it
really stays with our mission.
>> Yeah. And one of the the big challenges
that that y'all were sharing with me in
preparing for this uh podcast is that
there are so many free Zumba lessons on
YouTube at this point. 24 years in. I
love that it went all the way back to
VHS that the company started by sending
out VHS tapes. So you have 24 years or I
guess at the point where you start you
know started working on the app you know
21 22 23 years of content that's been
built up and not just by Zumba the brand
but by instructors by influencers maybe
even some people who don't even realize
Zumba was a brand and they just created
a YouTube video that says hey look at my
Zumba you know dance fitness how did you
think about not only balancing kind of
competing against the the instructors in
the live classes is, but then actually
building something that would
differentiate the app from just being
able to get free and and charging for
something when you could just go to
YouTube and get it for free.
>> Yeah, we actually specifically to the
YouTube question, we ask ourselves all
the time when building our road map, how
is this better than YouTube? How what
would make someone want to pay for this
when they can go to YouTube and get it
for free? And one thing that we learned
as we built the app, as we experimented
with different features was people were
looking for and were willing to pay for
a guided experience, not just a content
repository. So one thing that we built
and and tested last year was programs.
So instead of just dropping them into
the app and giving them a bunch of
content to choose from, we started
developing goal-based programs. So, as
they came in through onboarding, we
asked them about their goal, whether it
was weight loss, getting started, just
having fun or reducing stress. And then
we would build them uh content packages
or programs based on their goal. And it
gave people a lot less decision
paralysis. They were able to come in,
get to a program right away, get guided
through the classes that were the
perfect fit for them rather than having
to sort through content, which is what
they have to do on YouTube. So, once we
built programs, we saw a huge
improvement in our numbers. people that
joined programs um were watching two
times as many videos as people that
weren't enrolled in the programs. Our
month-to- retention went up. It about
doubled after for people that joined
programs. So, we saw that this was
really a differentiator for us and we
continued to build from there, releasing
more programs and building more features
that reduced this choice that users had
to make when they got into the app.
>> Yeah, it is such a fascinating thing. I
mean, so many apps are competing with
other apps, but you're also competing
with YouTube, you're also competing with
yourself, but also really cool that that
it's a broader business that you can
find success as a business if somebody
uses the app a few times and then starts
going to the live classes that still
benefit the business. But that
differentiation is key. Like, what is it
about the app that differentiates it
from other fitness apps, from free
YouTube content? any other kind of like
key insights or features or or things
that were kind of aha moments for the
Zumba team as you were building this out
that really became those kind of core
valuable pillars that people were
willing to pay for.
>> A lot of it for us was quality and
making sure that our content was super
high quality. The feedback that we got
from users was that when they went to
YouTube there was such a wide wide range
because you anybody can post a video and
like you mentioned they don't even have
to be doing Zumba. they just call it
Zumba and it's so hard to find what
you're looking for and people would tell
us that they would go through 5 10 15
videos um and they just don't have the
time or patience to do that. So we
really focused on highquality content
and we did a lot of research to figure
out what content it is that they wanted.
Um beginner content in the in the
beginning we had a lot of really varied
content. Um we still have a lot of
varied content but we learned from users
that a lot of people are looking for
beginner content because they're just
getting started. They're getting back
into fitness. So, we started really
filming a lot of high-quality beginner
content that can get them started. So,
just getting the really high-quality
content that users want, getting it in
front of them and guiding users to the
content that they are looking for as
soon as possible so we can get them to
that aha moment, which we've learned is
three classes. Um, so we see that once
users get to three classes, they're much
more likely to stay with us. So, they
really have to experience a little bit
of it and then they they stay and they
love it. I would want to add that uh of
course we've seen great improvements
over the year and a half, a lot of
learnings uh through features and also
acquisition and growth strategies, but I
think one thing that we're still looking
to unlock is how to build a a community
through the app. The magic of Zumba,
it's really in the power of the
community. We really don't think that it
can be replaced with a virtual
experience. I think the in-person
experience is is always going to win.
But uh we've tried with some basic
feature of community. we we didn't
succeed, so we turned it off. But we
this year and hopefully next year, we're
going to have the we're going to
dedicate time into thinking how can we
make and build communities online
through the Zumba app. Uh so we can
actually enable what happens a little
bit, you know, replicate a little bit
what happens into the in-person class.
>> Yeah. And that's such an interesting
kind of growth factor too in that the
magic of community in person is
incredible. Like you said, you can't
replicate that for I mean probably
hundreds of millions of people around
the world. Even though you're in 180
countries, there might not be a local
Zumba class that they can join. So
finding ways to to replicate some of
that magic, get a little hint of the
magic inside the app could be a really
powerful unlock for that kind of next
phase of growth.
>> Uh so yeah, really fascinating that you
try any kind of lessons from from having
failed? uh like what do you think didn't
work about the your first attempt at
that?
>> So our first attempt at community was we
had done some research and tested a few
hypotheses for where we wanted to start
and our hypothesis was that people want
to talk about the classes after they
take them. Um so we ended up building a
bunch of different chat threads that you
could join and talk about the classes or
talk about a health journey or talk
about um just starting out Zumba. And we
kind of were thinking, you know, if if
you build it, they will come. And we
built these communities. And what we
found was that people really didn't want
to engage, not in the context of the
class. They weren't looking to take the
class and then go into a community and
talk about it. So, in the next
iteration, we're thinking about how we
can do community a lot more
contextually. And this kind of goes back
to being in a live class. You know,
you're in the class, you're engaging,
you're high-fiving people in the class,
you're talking to your instructor after,
your instructor's asking you for
feedback. I'm smiling at Lucy. Lucy's
smiling back at me. There's all of these
different interactions in a class that I
think are a lot more powerful than this
approach of people wanting to discuss
the class um before or after. So, that
was what I believe didn't work for us.
And we're going to try again with a more
contextual approach.
>> Community is so tough. So hopefully
people can can learn some lessons from
from that and and keep an eye on what
Zumba does because I'm I'm sure as you
continue iterating uh you're going to
find something that does work and that a
lot of other apps will will learn from.
The next uh kind of section I wanted to
talk about is iteration. And I've really
appreciated kind of the growth mindset
I've heard from both of you in preparing
for the podcast is that there there does
seem to just be a real growth mindset
that even though you know you had a big
launch with the initial launch of the
app in 2024, there's just been hundreds
of iterations and a constant like small
tweak to this, small tweak to that and a
constant kind of growth mindset. Um
before we dive into like specific
experiments and some of the things
you've been working on lately, any any
kind of higher level thoughts about how
you approach and how you instill this
growth mindset with the team and and at
a 24 year old brand, you know, that is
kind of unique to have such a growth
mindset. So any thoughts there?
>> Yeah, it's such an interesting point. So
it it was a challenge in the beginning
for sure because
Zumba we have established departments we
have established pricing we have I mean
we always are looking for our next lever
or what else can we do to continue to
improve the business and continue to
grow but at a much different pace than
what we're doing with the app. So the
app is a small team. It's a very small
team. Super agile. And we got into this
growth uh iteration like test, fail,
move on, test, you know, succeed, move
on. And even when we're having good
results, we never settled. We're always
thinking, okay, what else can we do?
Should we do another pay wall test to
continue to improve the results? So it's
a it's a small team. And I think in this
case, it helps because they they really
allow us to move fast. And it's just a
culture that we've built in the past
year and a half. But it hasn't been
easy. It's been a process, but uh I
don't know, Nicole, how you feel, but
I'm super proud of the progress that
we've been able to make both on the on
the results, but also on the on the team
culture. We do a lot of great research
before going into our next feature um
building out our road map. But we treat
every new launch as a experiment and as
a hypothesis that we're testing. So when
we launch something, we are constantly
checking the metrics. We're constantly
checking the performance. um when
something isn't working, we'll do that
analysis and we'll say, "Hey, it's not
working. Let's try something else." So,
we're not, you know, married to any of
our ideas, no matter where it came from.
We just want, we all want the app to be
better. We all want to see continued
growth. So, we treat everything like a
continued experiment. And even features
that we launched last year, we check in
on them and say, "Is this still working
for our users? Is this still delivering
the results that we need?"
>> What does your stack look like? Are you
using like amplitude or mix panel and
are you using like a AB testing tool
specifically or using that inside a
product analytics like what does the
stack look like and how do you like dive
into the data to better understand how
those things are performing.
>> Um so we use mix panel heavily and we
also use an internal tool that we built
for AB testing. So the combination of
that with Mix Panel, we're constantly
looking at AB test data, retention,
churn, acquisition data, a lot of
different performance metrics uh that
we've built into the app,
everything. We're looking at it every
day. Lucy and I usually by 8 a.m. we're
pinging each other about what we're
seeing in the data in Mix Panel.
>> Revenue Cat has been a great tool for us
to to test pricing and pay walls. Um so
super happy and and also look at the
metrics. So we have like three sources
of of data. So, one of the big things I
want to dive into because I think a lot
of folks are really curious about this
right now is appto. I don't know who
came up with the web two app, the web
number two app, but now because that
became the the standard way to say it.
I've started saying app to web with the
number two. But with the recent
injunction against Apple that does allow
linking out, I know a lot of people are
starting to experiment with that and
seeing mixed results, but y'all seem to
be doing pretty well with it. So tell
me, you know, what you've been
experimenting with and and how that's
gone.
>> Nicole can explain better what we've
been experimenting, the actual product
changes, and I can talk about the
results. So really high level uh we've
done two iterations uh of testing and
what we've seen is that there is
definitely an initial drop in
conversion. So we lose about 35% of the
people converting either to a trial or a
paid. So our pricing is we have annual
at 99 with a 7-day trial and we also
have the 1499 monthly price with no
trial. So we've seen that that initial
conversion uh we saw a drop initially of
about 35%. With the second iteration we
managed to improve that to about 25%
drop instead of 30 35 but because
conversion from trial to paid on the
annuals is much better on web. we recoup
some of that loss and on top of that uh
obviously through web we have much
better retention and the lifetime value
therefore it's better and we avoid the
Apple Apple fees so when we look at
everything together we see a 17% lift on
lifetime value that more than offsets
the drop in in the initial conversion we
use the revenue cat tools to build this
so that initially we tested before the
package selection feature was available
with revenue cat we initially tested
just letting people check out um click
the app payw wall, go to the web, and we
compared that against just the inapp
payw wall. And then once Revenue Cat
released the package selection, we
developed it so that users could
actually choose which one they wanted
monthly or annually, which package. And
once they chose that, we would send them
to the web and we gave them the most
stripped down view on the web where we
just showed them what they selected. We
tried to replicate how Apple has that
view, has that window on the app when
you do an inapp purchase so that it
looks very familiar and that actually
helped us with the conversion a lot as
Lucy mentioned. So with the payw wall,
are you showing inapp and web or are you
showing only web? And then in these
experiments, were you AB testing
specifically one payw wall that was only
inapp purchase and one payw wall that
was only web or tell me what how you've
been setting up those payw wall tests.
More specifically,
>> the tests that we've done so far, we
were testing just only inapp versus only
web. Lucy mentioned we're still
continuing to improve on this. So even
though we've seen a big jump in our
lifetime value, we know that there's
still room to improve the conversion
that we see drop when we send them to
the web. So in the future, we're talking
about testing some other approaches. For
example, a payw wall that allows them to
check out either they can choose between
checking out on the web or the app. And
we're also thinking about some other
experiments to try to improve the
conversion.
>> Gotcha. So, so then the way the payw
wall currently works now with the
package selection would be that it looks
like a standard like inapp payw wall,
right? So, you have a monthly selector,
annual selector, and then you have the
call to action button of, you know,
check out, continue, subscribe, whatever
that actually I'm curious what what's
the call to action on the button that
you've landed on.
>> We've landed on start today. um tested a
few different ones and expert today
seems to be motivating for people and
also hopefully encourages them to
actually go and try their first class.
So that's where we are right now.
>> Gotcha. Okay. So then package selection
and then a a big button that says start
today as your call to action. And so
when they tap start today, it bounces
out to Safari, but then that page on
Safari is super stripped down. No more
package selection, no other options,
just a checkout button. And then what
are you using on the I I guess Zumba
having been around 24 years you already
had uh payment system and other things
that you had built out on the web but
are you offering Apple Pay or what is
that web checkout experience like?
>> We use Stripe for the web checkout
experience but they can also pay with
Apple Pay or Google Pay and one of the
optimizations that we've made that we've
seen um help us a little bit with the
conversion is we default to what we see
that the user has available. So, if they
have Apple Pay, we'll default to that
one selected first. If they have Google
Pay, we'll default to that one first.
And if they don't, then they'll just uh
see the credit card option.
>> Gotcha. Yeah. One of the feedback we got
on Revenue Cats test with our app dipsy
was that when you go to the checkout
page, it was like kind of a big form and
so even though it said like Apple Pay,
you know, at the bottom, it still looked
like you had a lot of work to do. So I
imagine like what you're saying is you
detect in the web browser that they have
Apple Pay available and then you don't
even show a credit card form, right? You
just show like check out with Apple Pay,
>> right? We just we make it as simple as
possible if they have Apple Pay.
>> Nice. Yeah, I I can see why that's
increasing conversion. That's the next
test we should probably do with the with
the dipsy payw wall on the web. One
debate that we had internally was
whether we give an extra incentive to
get people to subscribe through web but
we decided to test it without it because
obviously we wanted the help on the on
the lifetime values. We didn't want to
give that extra incentive and and I
don't know that people know so much the
difference between you know with this
seamless experience I don't think there
is uh there is so much hesitation and
we're seeing it in the numbers right we
still have room for improvement in that
initial conversion but I think we've
done we've done well this is one of the
most successful tests that we've had
>> yeah I mean a 17% increase in lifetime
value is fantastic one of my theories
about how this is all going to play out
in the long run is that apps will
eventually start to get a little more
sophisticated during onboarding to kind
of understand user intent and kind of
find those higher intent users and send
those to the web to help offset some of
that decline in conversion. You know, it
was a big drop 35% drop in conversion on
that first test and then great to see
that trial to paid did help offset that
and then further tests have even further
reduced that drop in conversion. But how
are y'all thinking about potentially
adding another layer in there?
Potentially sending some of those lower
intent users and just make keeping them
in the app to make sure it's like ultra
seamless. What are you thinking on that
front?
>> One thing that we're thinking about
doing is optimizing the payw wall for
where they are in the app. So changing
the message, changing the payw wall,
potentially changing which option we
give them based on where they are. So
maybe if they're in one of the places in
the app where the payw wall doesn't
convert as well like potentially some of
the ones that they see sooner in the app
or one of the ones that they see in the
settings potentially using some
different messaging or or just using the
inapp payw wall for that versus some of
the apps that we see converting really
well. For example, we have a welcome
class that we give them now. So when
they come in uh we give them one class
that they don't need to make a lot of
decisions and we say try this one first
and it's a fantastic beginner's class
and we see that payw wall doing pretty
well um because right after it we give
them a payw wall. So those seem to be
higher intent users. So maybe those are
the ones that we can send to app to web.
So we haven't done that yet, but it is
one of the things that we're thinking
about.
>> Yeah, it's a it's an interesting point.
We're just sending half of the people to
one experience versus the other. We're
not being very cautious about it, but
it's a it's a great point to look at the
data, understand which are higher intent
users, and based on that, maybe present
them with the the correct option. And
then just to kind of fully close the
loop, you've made the checkout
experience as seamless as possible with
the Apple Pay button and everything
else. And I imagine as soon as they've
checked out, there's a button. Does it
auto redirect right back to the app or
there's a button they press and they get
right back into the app? And kind of
like it's almost like a seamless you
bounce to the web, make your payment,
and bounce right back to the app.
>> Exactly. We tried to when we were
building out the experience, our north
star was let's make this look as much
like the inapp purchase as we possibly
can. And so we auto redirect them right
back and we try to make it as close to
the inapp purchase as possible.
>> Gotcha. Yeah. Yeah, that makes a lot of
sense. Yeah. Again, some of the feedback
we got from folks on our Dipsy
experiment and our experiment didn't do
too bad. I mean, we only saw a 6% drop
in realized LTV on the initial
conversions. Uh, which is not that bad.
And then to to your point on LTV, what
we see in the data is that far fewer
people on the web have turned off
autorenew. And so, you know, we're not,
you know, calculating the exact
predicted LTV of of what that's going to
be because they're all annual plans, but
it's looking like the LTV is going to be
higher on the web over the long haul,
even though it was a 6% loss in that
initial revenue conversion. So yeah,
this app to web is is going to be
interesting as people start to discover
the best practices and iterate their way
toward toward making it work.
>> Yeah, and it it can be very scary
because you can see CPA climb and and
you're like, oh, like you know, let me
turn this off because if you don't focus
on the big picture, you always get
caught up on the CPA
>> increasing, which is something that we
saw. But then when you do the lifetime
value calculation, I think that's when
you see the value, right? Well, on that
uh topic of retention, I know you have
done a lot of experimentation and
iteration on better retaining users. So,
tell me about some of your work there.
>> One of the things we've done with
retention is trying to celebrate their
wins and make them feel good about
taking classes and and try to help them
come back. So, we've done a lot of work
here. One thing we did was a postclass
experience. So after they take the
class, instead of just letting them drop
back into the app, we celebrate them. We
tell them that they did a great job. We
built a badge system, a gamification
system, and they can reach different
milestones. They can earn different
badges. There's number of classes taken
or there's number of steps taken. Um so
we do a lot of we spend a lot of time
celebrating them after the class. We
also have started to ask them to rate
the class after to improve our
recommendation algorithm. So now when
they take a class, we ask them if they
liked it. We ask them if it was too
hard, too easy, too intense, not intense
enough. And right away, we recommend
them the next class that they should
take. And when they sign back into the
app, we have it right there when they
sign in at the top of the app. So, we're
really trying to complete that loops for
them so that they can come back in and
they can take their next class. So,
we've seen that really improve the
amount of people coming back and taking
their next class. Um, just trying to get
them to the right class for them. We've
also worked a lot on our communication
journey. So, when is the right time to
send them a push notification? When is
the right time to send them an email?
We're working on a few things right now
to try to get their stats from the week
sent to them so that they can really
celebrate their wins and move on to
their next week with confidence. So,
we've done we've done a lot there.
>> When is the right time to send a text
message versus a push versus an email?
I'm sure people are like you you kind of
breezed over that. What are what are
some of the lessons there?
>> We're definitely still experimenting a
lot with that. we're we're checking the
performance of our emails and our push
notifications and making changes um when
our notifications aren't getting opened
or when they are leading to optouts,
we'll change it. But one of the things
we're doing right now that we're testing
is we're testing sending them a
notification at the time that they
usually go into the app. We say if a
user typically works out on Mondays, we
know that they're probably higher intent
there. Let's send them a notification
and remind them um that they can take
their class. or one thing that we're
trying is we see that usually going into
the weekend, Fridays, we see a little
bit of an activity dip. Um people are
getting ready for the weekend. So, we're
trying a notification there kind of on
the flip side to see if we can get them
excited about maybe take a shorter
class, maybe take a fun class um and
trying to suggest some things where they
might not otherwise um work out. But
timing wise, we're trying to send them
the notification at the time that
they're usually active also. So, you
know, if someone is typically active at
9:00 a.m., we're trying to time it so
that we send it at the time that they're
active versus, you know, if they're
never in the app in the middle of the
day, maybe they're working. We don't
want to send them a notification at 3
p.m., for example, if there's someone
that's not available then. So, we're
we're still testing this a lot.
>> Yeah, that's great. Some great lessons
there, though.
>> Yeah. And just to add to the previous
point uh regarding retention, I think
one of the biggest shifts which Nicole
talked a little bit about it in the
beginning was really focusing on that
audience, the beginner audience. We saw
that about 70 even more% of the people
coming through on boarding were saying
that they were beginners. We did
research to validate that. So now really
we're really focusing the product on on
that beginner experience, the intensity
of the classes, the complexity of the
classes to try to cater for that
audience to make them feel like they can
accomplish, you know, the workout and
that they can feel as winners as they
can be.
>> And I know you've experimented on
onboarding with longer onboarding and
shorter onboarding and adding friction,
removing friction. uh what are some of
the lessons there in onboarding that
you've learned and then how have you
continued to optimize that towards that
those downfunnel metrics and that longer
time horizon?
>> Yeah, definitely. I think this was a
lesson in just challenge all of your
assumptions that you have because for a
while in the beginning um we were
operating as if it was just best to get
the user to the payw wall as quickly as
possible, get them into the app and to
the payw wall as quickly as possible.
But um we had a hypothesis about longer
onboarding. And we started experimenting
with guiding the user through an
onboarding experience that kind of got
to know them a little bit. Also gave
them some interstitials during
onboarding to show the value of the app.
And we saw that that onboarding
experience actually led to a much higher
conversion than without having the
longer onboarding. And it also gave us
the ability to personalize what they saw
right when they got into the app. So, we
asked them a little bit about what they
were interested in, about what their
level was. And we were able to recommend
them a program before they even saw the
app. And doing this just helped them see
that we're listening to them, we know
who they are, and we have what's right
for them in the app. That greatly
increased our conversion. And I think it
was a surprise to a lot of us that we
introduced friction, but it really did
help us. And one thing we did after
introducing the long onboarding was we
actually introduced a payw wall before
the users even got into the app which
was another assumption that we
challenged was that oh no they
definitely have to see the product
before we showed them the payw wall. But
we were able to build enough value
perception into the onboarding
experience where we showed them a payw
wall right after onboarding before they
dropped into the product and that really
helped with overall conversion as well.
>> I heard one of you mention that that you
now just give away one free class. Where
did that come into the mix and how do
you introduce that in the onboarding
funnel and and whether they start a free
trial or not? I guess just to better
understand as well is the is the app
kind of hard paywalled where you really
only get that one class unless you start
the free trial.
>> No. So you can have that free class
without necessarily having to start the
free trial. We do get a lot of feedback
still about users again because Zumba is
so popular saying that they want more
free classes. So we we always have this
internal debate of like should we just
keep it to one class or should we can
can we give them access and I'm always
pushing back because obviously I want
the LTV to ratio to always work and I'm
always pushing back saying like let's
just keep that one class focus that
class on beginner and try to get them to
start their trial because they also have
an option to navigate the entire app and
access all the classes if they want it
with their with their free trial. So
that's why we landed on on that one
class. Normally when they go through on
boarding they see the paywell a big
percentage of them convert but then the
other big percentage that doesn't
convert has direct access access to that
free class if they choose to take that
class whenever they cut it off even if
they don't go through the entire class
we present a pay wall. So that's a
payable that as Nicole was explaining
before, maybe we can contextualize it a
little bit more because we get hundreds
of thousands of views in that class and
we can do a better job at converting
people from that experience.
>> Is that one class the same for every
user or are you actually using the
personalization to personalize that one
free class?
>> The one free class right now is the same
for every user. The reason we did it
like that is because the class is a
Zumba 101. So no matter who they are,
even if they take Zumba, it's a really
good introduction to what you're going
to see in the app. So it shows the basic
steps. It kind of gets them familiar
with the app format content. So for
right now, we're showing everyone the
same. But I think it's definitely a
possibility in the future that we
personalize that welcome class as well.
>> Yeah, I just wanted to add as we are
trying to prioritize the road map and
what else do we do next? As we're seeing
more than 75% of the people coming
saying that they're beginners, the Zumba
101 seems like a good fit for for the
majority. But eventually, I think there
could be more more room for
personalization.
>> Yeah. Or even five different Zumba 101
classes where it is still a Zumba 101,
but maybe it's just a little more
focused on on the different aspects that
that people are looking for. But I do
love that, you know, as you were talking
about introducing that friction. I mean,
so many apps now will do the long
onboarding, ask all these questions, but
then not actually do any level of
personalization. But it sounds like once
they do start the free trial, you take
into account a lot of that to then
recommend those best classes that are
going to be more retentive and a better
experience based on that
personalization.
>> Yeah, absolutely. We start influencing
their recommendation algorithm as soon
as they start the onboarding, whether
they start on the web or the app. So, as
soon as they drop in, they already have
a curated class experience. What do you
consider your aha moment or or what are
you kind of optimizing toward one class
toward some other experience or what do
you optimize toward?
>> Uh we found that three classes seems to
be the aha moment. After three classes,
they really seem to be much more likely
to be a long-term user. So we're trying
to get them to the three classes where a
lot of our communication early on is
focused on getting them to the three
classes. We have a class counter on the
homepage encouraging them to get to
three. In the onboarding, we actually
have them set a goal for how many
classes they want to commit to for each
week. We default that goal to three. And
we also have a little blurb about how
just three classes a week can really
help you see progress toward your goal.
So, we encourage them to choose that
three because we've seen that it helps
that others in the app have succeeded
with the three. And then throughout the
app, we have some small reminders to get
them to the three as well as the
communication journey.
>> Gotcha. I wanted to talk a little bit
about price testing. So, you know, Lucy,
you had mentioned early on that, you
know, at the corporate level, you know,
you've had prices and iterated on price
over a very long 24 year history. How
did you approach price testing in the
app and what are some of the lessons you
you learned there? Yeah, for the core
business, we were super careful with
pricing. So, we hire research companies,
pricing study companies, and we take
years before we make any change because
we already have such a large community.
For the app, we started with uh with
research on what we thought people were
willing to pay. But as you know, once
you're live, it is completely different
than the than the research. You try your
best, but things can change. And that's
when the culture of like testing and
iterating really matters. So, we started
with the monthly and the annual plans,
but both of them were free trials. We
believe in the beginning our monthly
price price was $19.99 and the yearly
price was $129
and we were seeing like really not great
conversion. So, we started to iterate.
We use revenue cut to AB test uh
different pricing packages and after a
lot of different testing which I still
think that we have room for improvement
uh we are now at monthly $14.99 no free
trial which led to great results so I
highly recommend it for anyone that is
hesitating definitely try it and then
contrary to many fitness apps we just
give a 7-day trial on the annual plan a
lot of apps give 30-day free trials or
even 14-day trials but we saw that you
getting them to a shorter trial led to
higher commitment, higher engagement,
them rushing into giving it a try and
and we actually didn't see a drop in
conversion. We saw a huge improvement in
conversion from trial to paid. So when
we started with uh with the app about
30% of our users even a little bit less
were choosing the annual plan and the
conversion was in the 30s from trial to
paid. At this point we are getting about
60% of the users choosing the annual
plan and about 56% conversion from
annual conversion from trial to paid on
the annual. So nice.
>> Yeah. And it's a combination right? It's
not only the pricing or the or the
packages is the app to web and it is the
first time user experience and the
beginner content and it's it's exciting
to see how everything combined really
can lead to good results.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And the nice thing there too
is without the free trial on the
monthly, then you are getting $15
upfront from the users who are choosing
that, which I do think is fair in that,
you know, $15 you'd pay that to go do
your first Zumba class in person or
whatever. Um, and so 25% of the users
are paying you upfront without even
starting that free trial. And then now
75% are doing the free trial and and
landing on annual. So, it seems like a
really great outcome for the business
and and a fairer, you know, trade-off
for the users.
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> All right. Well, I think that's a really
great place to wrap up. It's so fun
talking through all these iterations,
all the learnings, and and just fun
talking to a couple folks with a real
growth mindset at a company that's been
around 24 years like we keep talking
about. So, thank you for for sharing the
insights and it sounds like you've got
hundreds of more tests to do over the
next couple years and I think we'll be
seeing a lot more uh about Zumba in the
app community in the coming years. So,
thanks for joining me and thanks for
sharing so many insights.
>> Thank you for having us. Thank you,
David.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com.
subclub.com to join our private
community.
[Music]